Okay
everybody, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, sorry for the delay. Okay, we start
the new and the final מסכת Masechet in נזיקין, Nezikin, הוריות, Horayot,
and actually it makes a lot of sense what this מסכת Masechet
is doing, I don't think we ever fully explained or I really
fully know what עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is doing in נזיקין, Nezikin,
you know, maybe there was some of these things that there wasn't
any good other place to put them, but הוריות Horayot at least
has a logical continuation of סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, מכות, Makkot, and מכות Makkot
because סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות Makkot after you deal with the structures
of civil laws, civil laws, you know סנהדרין Sanhedrin and criminal laws
I guess, you know סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות Makkot deal with both,
well, some, the בבות Bavas all deal with the civil laws, סנהדרין
Sanhedrin part of it deals with like the laws that you get
lashes and מיתות misas or all the various sort of laws in
which בית דין Beis Din will punish for, and then it deals
with all the structures and the administrations of the court, that's סנהדרין
Sanhedrin and מכות. Makkot. And הוריות Horayot talks about what happens also
about the authority of the court, what happens if the court makes
a mistake in ruling. I mean it tends to start more with
issues around איסור והיתר, Issur V'heter, like a classic example is if
they say a certain כשר kosher fat is a טרייף treif non-kosher
fat, חלב chelev is שומן shuman is כשר kosher and so on,
but it also gets to, you know, other areas as well and
about the sacrifice that they bring, the special sacrifice if they rule
incorrectly, and then it gets to the questions about a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol and the זקן ממרא, Zaken Mamre, the person who rebels
against the authority of the court. So הוריות Horayot is actually a
nice, it is about authority and institutions of authority and legal authority
in general, political authority and so on. It's a nice continuation of
סנהדרין Sanhedrin and מכות. Makkot. It's a very short מסכת, Masechet, it's
the shortest מסכת. Masechet. There's also, if you'll notice, that every דף
daf sort of is the רש״י Rashi is really on both sides
of the page, the תוספות Tosafot is assigned to like the margins,
the thing here that's called תוספות Tosafot is a very, very short
תוספות, Tosafot, the תוספות הרא״ש Tosafot HaRosh which has also been put
here is a more standard sized תוספות. Tosafot. So anyway, if I
quote from תוספות Tosafot it'll most often be the תוספות הרא״ש. Tosafot
HaRosh. There's not a lot of ראשונים Rishonim on it, but it
is an interesting one in terms of like the political, you know,
sort of thinking of the rabbis. Okay, so with that let's get
started. First משנה Mishnah here on דף ב עמוד א. Daf Bais
Amud Aleph. הורו
בית דין לעבור על אחת מכל מצות האמורות בתורה. Horu Beis Din
la'avor al achas mikol mitzvos ha'amuros baTorah. The בית דין Beis Din
ruled to say that somebody-
that one of the מצות, mitzvos, they said that you could actually
violate something. They didn't actively say it's permissible to violate something. They
interpreted a law in a way that would lead to something that
should have been understood to be prohibited they actually said oh in
this case it's okay. Like let's say they actually said they were
discussing about what type of the fat of the בהמה, beheimah, the
חלב chelev is that that the תורה Torah forbids, and they actually
said that like the fat over here is not a problem and
it turned out they made a mistake that fat actually was forbidden.
Or another example, let's say they said לא תבשל גדי בחלב אמו
Lo sivashel gedi bachalav imo only means if you actually use the
mother's milk, if you use some other milk it's okay. Okay, so
they actually said that something that would have been forbidden actually they
interpreted the law in a way that it turned out it was
permissible, and they're making a mistake. So I should again say that
the beginning of הוריות Horayot focuses on like two פרשיות parshiyos in
the תורה, Torah, one is in דברים Devarim which is the case
of זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre which is the case about somebody who
rebels and rejects the authority of the court, and the other is
the case about what happens if והיה אם מעיני העדה נעשתה לשגגה,
v'hayah im me'einei ha'eidah ne'estah lishgagah, if they rule incorrectly and somebody
follows them or the community follows them, the ציבור, tzibbur, all of
ישראל Yisrael follows them and they have to bring a קרבן korban
for the guilt for having ruled incorrectly and misled the ציבור. tzibbur.
So first of all, just holding the two of those in juxtaposition
is interesting because the idea that you would kill a זקן ממרא,
Zaken Mamre, you'd execute a זקן ממרא, Zaken Mamre, somebody who had
the temerity to reject the authority of the court, right, is an
idea that like oh you know the court is right regardless, like
the court has absolute authority, nobody dare you know reject their authority
and or challenge their authority. And then on the other hand you
have the idea that an acknowledgment that they can make a mistake
and be responsible for the mistakes of you know of what everybody
does because they recognize that they make a mistake. Okay, and we're
actually going to see in our משנה Mishnah and it's particularly ironic
when you think about the idea of זקן ממרא Zaken Mamre that
if somebody realizes they're making a mistake they're not supposed to listen
to בית דין. Beis Din. So on the one hand if you
if you sort of like you know publicly defy their authority and
put yourself up as an opposing authority and you go around and
preach to people "they're wrong they don't know what they're talking about
listen to me" and so on, then you're a threat to the
system and we're going to execute you, that's a זקן ממרא. Zaken
Mamre. But if basically privately you think they're making a mistake and
you don't listen to them and you do what you think is
correct and you're in a position that that judgment is actually one
that's a meaningful judgment, it's not like you're just סתם stam some
שמו shmo off the street, you know, then actually that's what you're
supposed to do and you're not supposed to listen to
them if you sort
of... The other thing that I should just mention at the outset,
which is fascinating about this, is the idea that there's such a
thing as an objective mistake. Since the, like what would it mean
if let's say the Supreme Court decided oh, we misread the Constitution
and here just to take a contemporary example, we realized that actually
for the last 200 years there was no right to bear arms,
it was only permissible in the context that if you're actually doing
it as part of a
militia. Okay, so does that mean that for the last 200 years
they ruled incorrectly? No, it was an old interpretation of the Constitution
and a new interpretation of the Constitution. So it's allowed to be
a new rule without basically defining that what had passed was a
mistake, right? And normally I think we would tend to think that
the rabbi's role in interpreting the תורה Torah would be the same.
If at one stage they said don't cook a goat in its
mother's milk meant literally that and later they said no, it means
in general meat and milk, or they did the reverse, right, they
whatever it is, we wouldn't say oh for the past thousand years
people were eating non-kosher food. We would say that was an old
interpretation, this is a new interpretation, at least that's what we moderns
would say. Okay. The very fact that the משנה Mishnah deals with
an idea that they could have made a ruling and people followed
them and then they said actually we made a mistake, here's what
the verse should have meant, you know, and that defines the past
as a mistake, that is itself fascinating from a perspective of the
rabbi's role in interpreting the תורה Torah and do we think there's
such a thing as some sense of like an objective meaning that
they could get wrong? Okay, so anyway so those are I mean
they're really fascinating concepts here. So let's take a look. So it
starts with saying that they interpreted a law and they gave a
ruling that said that some transgression was permissible. בהלכה
יחיד ועשה שוגג על פיהן Be-halacha yachid ve-asa shogeg al pihen and
a person and an individual followed them and he went and he
listened to them and he therefore unintentionally
erred and let's say he ate this forbidden fat. Now the reason
we give the example of forbidden, let's give a more contemporary example,
or immediately contemporary. חמץ בפסח. Chametz be-Pesach. It has to be something
that under other circumstances you would bring a sin offering. Okay. So
if you actually thought something was מצה matzah and it turned out
that it was חמץ, chametz, okay, that's a חייב כרת chayav kares
or whatever it was a שוגג shogeg you'd bring a קרבן, korban,
a חטאת. chatas. Okay. And if the בית דין beis din says
this thing here is actually מצה matzah and it actually I mean
not just a particular thing, certain types of bread made in a
certain way is מצה. matzah. Okay. And everybody goes and eats it
and everybody's thrilled and it's a פסח Pesach and we're having this
stuff that tastes delicious. And then after פסח Pesach they tell us
'Whoops, we made a mistake. It was real, it was really חמץ.'
chametz. Okay. So now if we had done that as individuals, we
would bring the קרבן חטאת. korban chatas. If the whole ציבור, tzibur,
the majority of כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael listens to them, they bring
the קרבן. korban. That's what we're going to get to. Okay. So
now we're dealing with though this case where they ruled it, if
everybody listens to them, בית דין beis din brings the קרבן. korban.
But you don't have everybody when they realize they're wrong. Now but
you don't have everybody listen to them. You have a few people
listening to them. Okay. And they're eating this stuff and then after
פסח Pesach they say 'Whoops, that was חמץ.' chametz. So, since it's
not the majority of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, בית דין beis din
is not going to bring a קרבן. korban. What about the individuals?
Do they have to bring the קרבן? korban? Right? They didn't do
anything wrong, they just listened to בית דין. beis din. So you
would think they're totally blameless and nobody brings a קרבן korban here.
So that's what this משנה Mishnah says. בהלכה יחיד ועשה שוגג על
פיהן. Be-halacha yachid ve-asa shogeg al pihen. He goes ahead and he
follows their ruling even though it's going to turn out to be
a wrong ruling. בין שעשו ועשה עמהם, Bein she-asu ve-asa imahem, whether
he ate the חמץ chametz
they went ahead and they ate this חמץ chametz first and then
he followed them, which certainly makes him blameless, they actually in practice
ate this stuff. Okay. או בין שעשו ועשה אחריהם, O bein she-asu
ve-asa achareihem, or they did it
so whether he did it together with them, they all decided let's
have a nice meal, okay and they invited him,
okay, או בין שלא עשו, o bein she-lo asu, or even if
they didn't eat it, they just issued their ruling ועשה ve-asa and
he did it, nevertheless in all those cases whether they acted or
not, as long as they gave the ruling, פטור, patur, he has
no blame, he doesn't, מפני שתלה בבית דין, mipnei she-tala be-veis din,
he relied on the בית דין, beis din, they're the legal authority,
so even if they afterwards issue a statement that they made a
big mistake, okay, they don't bring a קרבן korban because it's not
the majority of the ציבור tzibur and he doesn't bring it because
he's an individual.
Now, הורו בית דין וידע אחד מהם שטעו, Horu beis din ve-yada
echad me-hem she-tau, now, they gave that ruling, but one of the
members of the court knew that they were making a mistake. He
was yelling at them and telling them maybe got up and said
let the walls of the בית מדרש beis medrash bend in, okay,
he was telling them that they got it wrong. Okay. And he
knows they're making a mistake. או תלמיד והוא ראוי להוראה, O talmid
ve-hu ra'uy le-hora'ah, or even if he's not actually a member of
the court, he's like a clerk of the court, but he is
somebody that is of the level that in theory he could be
on the court, we're talking here by the way I should make
it clear, this בית דין beis din means the סנהדרין הגדול, Sanhedrin
HaGadol, the central authority of the Jewish people, okay, והלך ועשה על
פיהן. ve-halach ve-asa al pihen.
I know they're making a mistake but I say look at the
end of the day they're the court, they have the authority. I'm
going to follow them and I'll eat the stuff even if in
my heart I know that it's חמץ. Chometz. They said it was
it was מצה Matzah and I'm going to eat it. בין שעשו
ועשה עמהם Bein she'asu v'asah imahem so whether whether I did it
together with them בין שעשו ועשה אחריהם bein she'asu v'asah achareihem or
they did it first and I followed them בין שלא עשו ועשה
bein shelo asu v'asah or they didn't do it at all and
I just went ahead and ate it הרי זה חייב harei zeh
chayav in that case I actually do have to bring a קרבן
korban מפני שלא תלה בבית דין mipnei shelo talah b'veid din
at the end of the day I didn't say I'm relying on
them because I actually felt that they were making a mistake. So
therefore since at the end of the day that I cannot claim
that I actually am a שוגג. shogeg. Now that's interesting because again
it gets to this question of absolute truth. Like I might be
able to say look if I think that they're making a mistake
then
maybe they made a mistake like maybe I think that the Supreme
Court has been wrong for the last 200 years how they're interpreting
the second amendment you know but it doesn't mean that that's not
the law of the land right? So whether I think they're making
a mistake or not if they interpret it that way maybe that's
the law. So again what we get to the point is is
that there is some sense here it's not spelled out how maybe
in many cases that's true that it's an open interpretation and whatever
they say goes but there's some cases at least where there's a
sense that it's an objectively wrong פסק psak okay? And therefore and
therefore it is not a legitimate הלכה halacha even after they issue
that ruling. And therefore if that's true and I know that I
believe that to be the case I mean what does it mean
I know it? I believe that to be the case that they're
wrong I cannot say that I'm relying on their authority. It is
even after they said it it's not the law and if I'm
going to go ahead and do it then I'm going to knowingly
be breaking the law and I would have to bring a קרבן.
korban. Now the גמרא's Gemara going to ask then I should be
מזיד meizid like if I know it's a wrong ruling and I'm
doing it anyway so we'll get to that okay? But anyway so
that's the case זה הכלל zeh haklal this is the rule התולה
בעצמו חייב hatoleh b'atzmo chayav
if you're relying at the end of the day on yourself you're
not sort of saying they know better than I do you actually
do think they're wrong then you bring a קרבן. korban. התולה בבית
דין hatoleh b'veid din if you're relying on them פטור patur then
you are exempt from a קרבן. korban. At the end of the
day you're following them.
Yes? Doesn't that cause some confusion if some people are doing it
one way and other people are doing it another way?
Well yeah I mean that gets to well first of all the
number of people that actually would not listen first of all would
not listen to the court would be small because it would only
be the people that were like on the בית דין Beis Din
themselves or were fit to be on the בית דין Beis Din
but the question also what we're dealing here mostly since we're talking
about doing an active עבירה aveira to not listen to the court
means just to be passive. You know what I mean? It means
like so fine I won't eat that on פסח Pesach I'll eat
my normal מצה matzah on פסח Pesach you know? So it's not
like I'm actively doing something different. It just means I'm choosing this
thing they said was a permissible act I'm just choosing not to
do it. So that's also now but the other question of course
is like I said reading this alongside the whole idea of זקן
ממרא zaken mamre because the whole problem of a זקן ממרא zaken
mamre is somebody who actively defies the authority of the court and
of course the person who's actively defying the authority of the court
believes in his mind that he's totally right and they're totally wrong.
So isn't that this person? And part of the difference is exactly
this is that the זקן ממרא zaken mamre goes out and preaches
to everybody and sets himself up as an opposing authority. This guy
just personally is making a private choice you know not to do
it. Okay? If now if this guy said like oh my God
this is חמץ chometz I can't eat this and then I'm going
he's going to go around and tell everybody don't listen to them
don't listen to them it's חמץ chometz or whatever right? That's a
problem because then he's not just acting as a private you know
then he's so it's a funny you know you could say he's
trying to save them from עבירה aveira but nevertheless that's where it
crosses a line and becoming a competing authority with the court.
It reminds me of a little bit of כשרות kashrus in ישראל.
Yisrael. Yeah. Where like
my theory was always if the רבנות Rabbanut says it's כשר kosher
I don't ask questions. Right. And a lot of people they say
the רבנות Rabbanut is a certain like ambiguous baseline but if you
look behind the scenes you'll find out that a lot of the
things aren't really כשר. kosher. Right right right. And the question is
kind of do you just follow the רבנות Rabbanut or do you
like go in and try to think they're טועים to'im and follow
something else?
Right right right. That's a good question.
Yeah yeah yeah. Like a central authority is like giving like their
stamp of approval.
Their stamp of approval and exactly and how much does that free
you from responsibility? What does a lay person ever in a position
about like תלמיד וראוי להוראה? talmid v'raui l'hora'ah? Because let's say the
question about their error isn't about the הלכה halacha but it's about
the fact?
Right, and the רבנות. Rabbanut.
So right, let's say in this case of the משל mashal let's
say they made a certain assessment that a certain thing was permissible
and you said like yeah but I'm a doctor or I'm a
scientist and I know they misunderstood the facts right? So maybe that
would be a case where you're not ראוי raui to be on
the בית דין Beis Din but you also can't be תלה בבית
דין. talah b'veid din. And what you're talking is an example where
a lay person right now doesn't actively know they're wrong but maybe
they're in a position to do a little bit of digging and
investigation and how much does that shift the sense of where the
responsibility lies? That's an excellent question. Yeah it's an excellent way of
sort of framing this issue when are you תולה בעצמו toleh b'atzmo
and when are you תולה בבית דין? toleh b'veid din? So let's
take a look. אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel לעולם אין בית דין חייבין
עד שיאמרו להם מותרים אתם.
l'olam ein beis din chayavin
ad sheyomru lahem mutarin atem. בית דין Beis Din is not חייב.
chayav. Now it's funny what does he mean... Do a little bit
of digging and investigation and how much does that shift the sense
of where the responsibility lies? That's an excellent question. Yeah, it's an
excellent way of sort of framing this issue. When are you תולה
בעצמו toleh b'atzmo and when are you תולה בבית דין? toleh b'veis
din? So let's take a look. אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel לעולם אין
בית דין חייבין עד שיאמרו להם מותרין אתם. l'olam ein beis din
chayavin ad sheyomru lahem mutarin atem. בית דין Beis din is not
חייב. chayav. Now what does he mean when he says חייב? chayav?
We're talking about the individual being פטור. patur. But for now we're
assuming they're two sides of the same coin or that when a
if the majority of the community listens of of like the Jewish
people listen to the בית דין beis din then and they sin
then the בית דין beis din brings a קרבן. korban. Okay, so
when בית דין beis din makes a wrong ruling, minority who listens
to them according to our משנה mishnah is exempt and then nobody
brings a קרבן. korban. Majority, they bring a קרבן. korban. And therefore
the question is by framing both of those cases, when is it
considered that the individuals are following them? When have they issued an
official ruling and the individuals are following them? Both for the individuals
to be exempt and when the individuals become the majority for them
to be חייב. chayav. So שמואל Shmuel says that state that that
they gave an official ruling and then it exempts the individuals and
obligates them if it's a majority is only if they say the
word you are permissible, meaning the word is אתם. atem. They're not
saying in the abstract, it would be permissible for a person to
blah blah blah. That's like a theoretical statement, okay? It is permissible
for you, okay? This is permissible for you. Okay, מותרין אתם. mutarin
atem. רב דימי מנהרדעא Rav Dimi mi-Nehardea אמר amar עד שיאמרו להם
מותרין אתם לעשות. ad sheyomru lahem mutarin atem la'asot. It is permissible
for you to do this. They have to have that active word
to do it, otherwise it's still a theoretical point, you know, that
that they're sort of saying it. Now the תוספות ראש Tosafos Rosh
discusses that they might not need the magic word, it might contextually
matter. If I come to the בית דין beis din and it
says here's my case, dada dada, is it permissible for me to
eat this fat? And they say yes, it's permissible. They might not
need to say לעשות. la'asot. It's clear they mean that I have
a concrete case and they're giving me a ruling and I'm going
to act on it. But it's different. So that's what the לעשות
la'asot is doing, that they're responding to a concrete situation and that
makes it a real ruling and a practice. Okay, as opposed to
if they just sort of say you know like in general, like
it's like somebody's writing a תשובה. tshuvah. You ask me a question
and I say yes, permissible for you to do this. As opposed
to if I'm like writing a ספר הלכה sefer halacha and I'm
talking about in general like laying down the general parameters, but I'm
not giving a concrete specific ruling. And that becomes a whole discussion
in the גמרא Gemara like you know when some גמרא Gemara says
that you're not supposed to follow it when somebody says
הלכה halacha עד שיאמר הלכה למעשה. ad sheyomar halacha l'ma'aseh. It's not
just that they're saying that this is the ruling, but this is
the ruling for it to in practice. And sometimes a פוסק posek
is a little bit hesitant, he's making a big חידוש chiddush and
he doesn't want and he wants to sort of say like I
believe in theory this is the law but I'm not 100% ready
to say you should do it. We'll say להלכה ולא למעשה. l'halacha
v'lo l'ma'aseh. Like this is the law that I believe is correct,
but I'm not yet saying to act on it. Okay? So therefore
they say you need either the words or the context or the
concrete case to make it clear that this is a ruling meant
to be acted upon. And only then can you say that the
individual followed them and and all these special rules kick in. עד
שיאמרו להם מותרין אתם לעשות. ad sheyomru lahem mutarin atem la'asot. מאי
טעמא mai ta'ama why? לפי שלא נגמרה הוראה. lefi shelo nigmrah hora'ah.
It's not finished yet. It hasn't been made clear that it's to
be acted upon until that word or that context is there. אמר
אביי Amar Abaye אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanina. So
we have other evidence that you need that active verb to make
it a real binding sort of relevant ruling. Okay? חזר לו לעירו.
chazar lo l'iro. So here's the case about what makes somebody a
זקן ממרא, zaken mamre, the rebellious elder. So he voiced his opposition
and then he went back to his own town. שנה ולימד כדרך
שלימד, shanah v'limed k'derech she-limed, פטור. patur. If he continues teaching like
he says look the בית דין beis din rules that this is
the thing, I think that the following should be the right law,
okay? So if he talks about it and he's just talking about
it more in theory he's not a זקן ממרא. zaken mamre. הורה
לעשות, horah la'asot,
חייב. chayav. If he says this is how you should act, you
should listen to me, that's when he's a זקן ממרא. zaken mamre.
So the keyword being is לעשות. la'asot. Not just this is the
law, but this is how you should act. Okay, fine. חייב. chayav.
אמר רבי אבא Amar Rabbi Abba אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan
nami tanina. הורו בית דין להינשא והלכה
וקלקלה. horu beis din l'hinasay v'halcha v'kilkela.
A woman has a testimony of one witness that her husband died.
So that type of a case it's only one witness there's a
certain sense of that she might be responsible if the witness is
wrong or it requires the special license of בית דין. beis din.
So if בית דין beis din went and told her fine, we
accept the testimony of this one witness, it's permissible for you to
remarry. And then she went and rather than remarrying she just had
sex with another man outside the context of marriage. Okay, now you
should say implicit by saying it's permissible for you to be married
is that we are deciding that your husband is dead. But she
doesn't have an explicit license of the court to have sex. She
only general she only has a license of the court to remarry,
right? So even though implicit in their ruling is their decision that
the husband is dead, their practical permission, their practical what they are
telling her she's allowed to do is remarry. She's not they're not
telling her she's allowed to have sex outside of marriage. And therefore
if she has sex outside of marriage and then it turns out
that the husband is alive, then it's considered that she committed adultery.
You understand this? She gets married to a second guy and then
has sex with the second guy and the husband is alive she
didn't commit adultery. Well she did but she's and she's like, you
know, blameless. But it turns out that she had sex outside of
marriage and the husband was alive, then she's blameworthy for having committed
adultery. הכא דקלקלה חייבת בקרבן hacha dekalkela chayavet bekurban שלא התירו לה
להינשא. shelo hetiru la lehinnase. So even though look in theory what's
implicit in what they're saying is XYZ, it
doesn't matter. They haven't actually given you active permission to do that.
Okay, so it's not considered a real ruling that you can say
that you are acting based on you know their ruling and therefore
you're not acting on your own unless the ruling explicitly says here
is what you're allowed to do. Okay. So אמר רבינא אף אנן
נמי תנינא Amar Ravina af anan nami tenina so also so obviously
this is why it's circling back that's also our משנה. mishna. הורו
בית דין לעבור על אחת מכל מצוות האמורות בתורה Horo bet din
la'avor al achat mikol mitzvot ha'amurot baTorah so they הורו horu it
says לעבור. la'avor. That they didn't say that they הורו horu about
a mitzvah that something was permissible. They said they were they told
you that you could do this act and it turned out that
that act was a transgression. וחסלו מידי. vachasselu midi. That's sort of
the end of it, all of this tannaitic evidence proves that it's
only considered a פסק psak of בית דין bet din if they
say הלכה למעשה. halacha lema'aseh. Okay they actually give you an explicit
ruling. I have to tell you like it's true even nowadays you
see it in like a couple you know it's rare that people
like in America, in Israel it's very common, in America it's much
rarer that people write תשובות, tshuvot, you know that people actually write
practical rulings. And even in Israel some people complain that there were
some recent books that came out really actually very good הלכה למעשה
halacha lema'aseh books, ספרים sfarim that came out, but that at the
end they don't say here's the הלכה. halacha. You know, here's in
this case you are allowed to do this, don't do this, do
this, etc. They don't say that, they sort of say here are
the different opinions, like they talk more theoretical than really taking the
full responsibility even though it's clear what they want to be saying,
right, but they don't actually say in this case permissible for somebody
to do X. They sort of say like you know you know
the consensus of the פוסקים poskim is that the following thing is
permissible. You know you're talking in the abstract, right you're not actually
saying you are allowed to do that and that's actually saying that
yeah that is the full taking of responsibility of the court but
that's also what fully gives as it were license
to
the individual in these
various types of
cases. Okay. But you don't have a
court today so you
would rely on a פוסק
posek
to you could do that you could say if he gave me
this permission. Yeah exactly the same type of thing happens, you know
I'm relying on this פוסק posek and you know and then it
becomes like okay if you know better if you think they're making
a mistake and you're in a position to judge that's the case
of בר אוריין לא סגי. bar oryan lo sagi. But if you're
not you know in a position to know better and to judge
then yeah you're just following them. I mean we'll see a little
bit more about this about but presumably that makes you look blameless
you know you're just following the פסק psak that you got. Okay.
So now the גמרא gemara says like but it is interesting this
difference this line between a theoretical discussion and actually taking the responsibility
of saying no I'm telling you you're allowed to do it, rest
on my authority you're allowed to do it. Okay.
Okay
fine and the גמרא gemara says like this. You know that also
gives like you know it's like the זקן ממרא zaken mamre the
out. Like he can say I'm not telling anybody to do it
I'm just telling them this is what I think the הלכה halacha
is, you know? All right but that's like I said you see
that phenomenon nowadays. We're just talking about in theory what the הלכה
halacha is. Okay anyway פוק חזי. puk chazi. אמר שמואל אין בית
דין חייבין עד שיאמרו להם מותרים אתם לעשות Amar Shmuel ein bet
din chayavin ad sheyomeru lahem mutarin atem la'asot
that שמואל Shmuel said that they have to say לעשות la'asot like
we said before. I'm sorry it reverses it. It has שמואל Shmuel
being the one who says you have to say לעשות. la'asot. ורב
דימי מנהרדעא אמר אפילו מותרים אתם נגמרה הוראה. veRav Dimi miNehardea amar
afilu mutarin atem nigmera hora'ah. And רב דימי Rav Dimi says you
don't have to be that explicit even if you just say that
this is that this is permissible without sort of explicitly saying you
may do this, that itself is a sufficient and now it's going
to say everything we quoted before as a proof now we're going
to show as a contradiction because all the evidence shows that you
need to say לעשות. la'asot. אמר אביי ולאו תנן הכי Amar Abaye
velo tnan hachi didn't we teach that way? חזרו ליראה ושנו ולימדו
כדרך שלימדו פטור. chazaru leyira veshanu velimedu kederech shelimedu patur.
If you're just teaching the law you're exempt. הורה לעשות כזקן ממרא
דברי רבי אלעזר. hora la'asot kezaken mamre divrei Rabbi Elazar. If you
say you can do this act this way then חייב chayav you're
חייב. chayav. אמר רבי אבא ולאו תנן הכי Amar Rabbi Abba velo
tnan hachi didn't we teach that way? הורו בית דין להינשא והלכה
וקלקלה חייבת בקרבן שלא התירו לה להינשא. horu bet din lehinnase vehalcha
vekalkela chayavet bekurban shelo hetiru la lehinnase. If they permitted her to
remarry and she had sex outside of marriage then she's חייבת chayavet
a קרבן kurban because that's operating outside of the explicit ruling of
בית דין. bet din. So that shows you that it's not enough
that they what's implicit in their ruling it's only when they make
it explicit what you're allowed to do. אמר רבינא ולאו תנן הכי
Amar Ravina velo tnan hachi הורו בית דין לעבור על אחת מכל
מצוות האמורות בתורה horu bet din la'avor al achat mikol mitzvot ha'amurot
baTorah וחסלו מידי. vachasselu midi. Okay same as our משנה. mishna. All
of this evidence shows that the full הוראה hora'ah is not when
they say הלכה halacha or when they say הלכה למעשה. halacha lema'aseh.
Okay. Moving on now. והלך היחיד ועשה שוגג על פיהם. vehalach hayachid
ve'asa shogeg al pihem. So now the individual listens to them and
he follows them unwittingly. וניתני ועשה על פיהם uniteini ve'asa al pihem
why doesn't it just say the person listens to them? שוגג למה
לי shogeg lama li what does it mean he does it you
know unwittingly and he follows them? שוגג shogeg a classic שוגג shogeg
is a case where I accidentally do an
עבירה. aveirah. He says because there's a classic case of שוגג. shogeg.
What's a classic case of שוגג? shogeg? Classic case of שוגג shogeg
is, okay, this here is חלב, chelev, is forbidden fat, and this
here is שומן, shuman, is what do you call it, is kosher
fat. And I
actually know that I have some kosher fat here and I stick
my hand and I pick up this and I eat this, thinking
it was the kosher fat. In that case I accidentally did an
עבירה, aveirah, I ate the wrong thing and I would bring a
קרבן. korban. Okay, that's a classic שוגג. shogeg. Now, that's what שוגג
shogeg normally implies is something of that I was a certain degree
negligent, I should have been more careful. Okay, fine. Has nothing to
do with בית דין. Beis Din. Now, let's say we have exactly
this scenario except this non-kosher fat here, בית דין Beis Din actually
ruled it was okay.
Okay. So this case, I went to eat the שומן, shuman, I
accidentally ate the חלב, chelev, but this is חלב chelev that even
had I known what it was, I would have eaten it because
בית דין Beis Din gave the ruling. So that case, what do
we say? Do we say I'm שוגג shogeg because in my act
I was not consciously following בית דין? Beis Din? I was trying
to eat this. So in the end of the day I ate
this, but maybe, maybe it's only considered to be not my act,
I'm not responsible, if in my mind I am following בית דין,
Beis Din, because then you could say that action was all just
a part of בית דין's Beis Din ruling, you know, it was
following as an outcome of בית דין's Beis Din ruling. It's almost
like בית דין Beis Din told me to do it, don't look
at me, look at them. Okay. That's when I consciously ate this.
That's when I'm פטור. pattur. But let's say I accidentally ate this,
I was trying to eat this, then maybe ironically, even though I've
now made a double mistake, maybe ironically I'm חייב, chayav, because
arguably I would have eaten it even without בית דין's Beis Din
involvement. The fact that I ate this חלב chelev
has nothing to do with, that's a good way of saying it
also, meaning had they not ruled, I would have eaten it anyway,
because accidentally I would have eaten it anyway. Their ruling did not
make me eat it. Right. As opposed to when I'm consciously, their
ruling made me eat it, it's the reason I'm eating it. So
here their ruling is not the reason I'm eating it, and therefore
it should basically just be considered it's my act. Accidental, I'm not
מזיד, meizid, I bring a קרבן, korban, but I don't get to
shirk, I don't get to so to disassociate myself from the act,
right, because as it was said very well, like it's not like
I would have this would have happened had it not been for
their ruling. But in the case when it only happened because of
their ruling, I would say don't look at me, look at them.
So that's the question. In that case do I bring a קרבן
korban or not? So that's what רבא Rava saying is the reason
it says שוגג על פיהם shogeg al pihem is to tell you
two cases. One case of שוגג shogeg
that after their ruling I accidentally ate the wrong piece, and the
other case was I consciously did it because of their ruling. And
he actually says in both cases actually you are exempt, because at
the end of the day, right, their ruling would have been sufficient
to have had me eat this piece. All right. So רבא Rava
says, so that's what רבא Rava says is the משנה's Mishna teaching
you. Now, מלתא דפשיטא ליה לרבא, milsa depishite lei l'Rava, now this
thing that for רבא Rava himself was obvious,
I'm sorry, ואיכא דאמרי, v'ika d'amri, another say,
אמר רבא שוגג על פיהם הוא דפטור. amar Rava shogeg al pihem
hu depattur. No, it's telling you the exact opposite. That it's only
when your error is a direct result of their ruling. אבל נתחלף
לו חלב בשומן ואכלו חייב. aval nischalef lo chelev b'shuman v'achalo chayav.
If you accidentally got the pieces mixed up, חייב, chayav, then you're
חייב chayav because your error would have happened, you would have eaten
it regardless of their ruling.
Now, מלתא דפשיטא ליה לרבא, milsa depishite lei l'Rava, the thing that
for רבא Rava himself was obvious according to this version, okay, or
what either would have been, קמיבעיא ליה לרמי בר חמא. ka miba'ei
lei l'Rami bar Chama. So we have two versions, either for רבא
Rava it's obvious that you're exempt in that case or it's obvious
that you're חייב. chayav. But okay, so there's two different versions of
what רבא Rava said. But either way רבא Rava had a clear
position on this. רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama did not have
a clear position on this, דבעי רמי בר חמא, d'ba'ei Rami bar
Chama, because רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked, הורו בית דין
שחלב מותר ונתחלף לו בשומן ואכלו מהו? huru Beis Din shechelev mutar
venischalef lo b'shuman v'achalo mahu? בית דין Beis Din ruled that this
piece of fat
was permissible and he accidentally ate it, he was trying to eat
a different thing, ואכלו מהו? v'achalo mahu? So what's the הלכה? halacha?
So he asked it as a question. רמי בר חמא Rami bar
Chama didn't know. And now רבא Rava tries to resolve it. אמר
רבא תא שמע, amar Rava tashma, come and listen, here, הלך יחיד
ועשה שוגג על פיהם. halach yachid v'asa shogeg al pihem. שוגג על
פיהם למה לי? shogeg al pihem lama li? What's this extra word
accidentally following them? Why didn't it just say following them? לאו לאתויי
הורו בית דין שחלב מותר ונתחלף לו חלב בשומן ואכלו פטור? lav
l'asuyei huru Beis Din shechelev mutar venischalef lo chelev b'shuman v'achalo pattur?
So doesn't it mean that שוגג shogeg that even when he accidentally
eats the wrong piece he's also exempt after their ruling? So no,
דילמא שוגג על פיהם הוא דפטור. dilma shogeg al pihem hu depattur.
No, maybe only the reading is not שוגג shogeg or על פיהם,
al pihem, but a שוגג shogeg that's only because of what they
said. Only when he is actively following them is when he's exempt.
אבל נתחלף לו חלב בשומן ואכלו חייב. aval nischalef lo chelev b'shuman
v'achalo chayav. But if he's actually getting it mixed up and he
would have done it regardless, accidentally, but he would have done it
regardless, he's חייב. chayav. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amrei, some say אמר רבא,
amar Rava, Rava tried to resolve it the other way. תא שמע
הורו הורו בית דין ועשה שוגג על פיהם. ta shema horu horu
Beis Din v'asa shogeg al pihem. מאי לאו שוגג על פיהם הוא
דפטור? mai lav shogeg al pihem hu d'patur? So now reading this
as one phrase, not as two phrases. Only when the error is
directly as a result of their ruling, אבל נתחלף לו חלב בשומן
ואכלו חייב, aval nitchalef lo chelev b'shuman v'achalo chayav, but if it
gets the pieces get mixed up, he's חייב chayav because it's not
a result of their ruling.
So the גמרא Gemara says no, not necessarily. דילמא או שוגג או
על פיהם. dilma o shogeg o al pihem. Maybe either or. So
basically you can read the משנה Mishnah either way. There's an extra
word שוגג shogeg in the משנה, Mishnah, but it could come... there's
two ways to read it. It's coming to tell you either A
or not A, you know, we just don't know which one of
them. Okay, פלוגתא. plugta. Now this issue is actually a debate we'll
see of רב Rav and רבי יוחנן. Rebbi Yochanan. הורו
בית דין שחלב מותר ונתחלף לו חלב בשומן, horu Beis Din shechelev
mutar venitchalef lo chelev beshuman, exactly this case, ואכלו. ve'achalo. רב אמר
פטור. Rav amar patur. He's exempt. Since he'd be exempt by listening
to
בית דין, Beis Din, so here too, even though he got it
mixed up,
it would be something he would have eaten anyway.
רבי יוחנן אמר חייב. Rebbi Yochanan amar chayav. He's חייב chayav because
even without their ruling, he would have eaten it. Okay, so מיתיבי.
maysivi. I'll ask you on this. מעם הארץ בעשותה. me'am ha'aretz be'asosa.
It's a ברייתא. Braisa. It says if a person from the people
of the land does a sin, they have to bring a קרבן.
korban. This is a classic verse of, like the classic פרשה parsha
in the תורה Torah of where an individual brings a קרבן korban
for a sin. Okay, so what does it mean from the people
of the land and presumably not all of them? פרט למומר. prat
lemumar. This is excluding the case of an apostate, somebody who has
rejected. Like if somebody basically says, I don't believe in this whole
חלב chelev nonsense, I eat חלב chelev regularly. I eat בשר בחלב
basar bechalav regularly. Okay, so that type of a person that has
completely rejected and now rejected it. Here's a guy that basically... here,
we'll use a more contemporary example: חמץ בפסח. chametz be-Pesach. Somebody never
keeps פסח. Pesach. They always eat חמץ chametz on פסח. Pesach. Now
today, but you know, ליל הסדר Leil HaSeder they figured, all right,
I'll try to do this thing, I'll eat some מצה matzah and
they were going to eat some מצה matzah and accidentally they ate
חמץ. chametz. Okay, so that person and now they have regret. Do
they bring a קרבן korban for eating חמץ? chametz? So the answer
is no. Since you basically have rejected the whole thing altogether and
you would have eaten חמץ chametz even had you known it was
חמץ, chametz, therefore, even though here you ate it accidentally, you're not
going to bring a קרבן. korban. You got it? So that's the
person who's rejected this category of law. He is going to not
bring a קרבן korban even if he accidentally sins in this area.
פרט למומר. prat lemumar. רבי שמעון בן יוסי אומר משום רבי שמעון:
Rebbi Shimon ben Yossi omer mishum Rebbi Shimon: אינו צריך הרי הוא
אומר... eino tzarich harei hu omer... no, you can get it from
a different verse. אשר לא תעשינה בשגגה. asher lo sa'aseinah bishgaga. If
a person does a sin that you should not be doing but
in error. And the way this is reading is, he otherwise would
not have done but he's only doing it because he made a
mistake.
פרט לשב מידיעתו. prat l'shav mideiato. השב מידיעתו מביא קרבן, hashav mideiato
mevi korban, somebody who had he known would not have eaten it,
that's the person who brings a קרבן korban על
שגגתו. al shigagaso. לא שב מידיעתו, lo shav mideiato, somebody who even
had he been informed would have gone ahead and done it, אינו
מביא קרבן על שגגתו. eino mevi korban al shigagaso. Does not bring
a קרבן korban when he makes a mistake. So my example, the
guy you say, wait, wait, stop, that's חמץ chametz you're eating, it's
not מצה. matzah. This is a guy who would have said, I
don't care, I eat חמץ chametz on פסח Pesach anyway. Okay, so
that person would not bring a קרבן. korban. So it sounds like
they're both basically
having
the same ruling, just learning it from a different verse. There is
a slight difference which the גמרא Gemara elsewhere explores. That the idea
of מומר mumar basically excludes the whole person. You as a person
will never bring a קרבן korban for those types of sins because
you have rejected and you're a מומר. mumar. As opposed to in
this particular act, you, even had you known better, you would have
done. And focusing on the act is helpful for us in our
case. Because in our case, you're actually a צדיק. tzadik. You're not
a מומר. mumar. You listen to everything בית דין Beis Din says.
Okay, so in this case where these things got mixed up, right?
And you ate this but you were trying to eat this... excuse
me, you were trying to eat this,
which is the שומן shuman and you accidentally ate the חלב. chelev.
So in that case, you're a total צדיק, tzadik, you do everything
right. If I was to say, wait, בית דין Beis Din actually
ruled that this is actually... this is actually חלב, chelev, but בית
דין Beis Din ruled it's permissible. So that... so you would have
eaten it anyway, right? You get it? This is a case where
had you known the facts of what בית דין Beis Din ruled
and that you were eating חלב, chelev, but בית דין Beis Din
ruled this, okay, you would have done it anyway.
So לא שב מידיעתו. lo shav mideiato. It's not that you would
have done it anyway because you're such a
רשע. rasha. That's the other case. Here you would have done it
anyway because בית דין Beis Din gave a ruling and you're willing
to listen to בית דין. Beis Din. So you're not a שב
מידיעתו. shav mideiato. You're not a person who had you known better
would have stopped doing what you're doing. So that's the argument that
you should not bring a קרבן. korban. Okay, in this case of
the בית דין's Beis Din ruling. You would not have to bring
a קרבן. korban. Why? Because ultimately, even though you weren't actively following
בית דין, Beis Din, you would have been prepared to have eaten
it given בית דין's Beis Din ruling, and therefore you don't bring
a קרבן. korban. Okay, so... That's the logic. So that should support
the position of רב Rav that you don't bring a קרבן. korban.
ואם איתא Ve-im ita and if it's what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
said is correct, הלא שב מידיעתו הוא. halo shav midiato hu. In
this case, it's not—why wouldn't רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan say you're חייב
chayav a קרבן, korban, even had you known that you were eating
a חלב, chelev, you wouldn't have stopped eating it. So אמר רב
פפא amar Rav Pappa says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, קסבר רבי יוחנן,
kasavar Rabbi Yochanan, כיון דכי מישתודע להו לבי דינא keivan de-ki mishtoda
lehu le-vei dina הדרי בהו hadari behu והוא נמי הדר ביה, ve-hu
nami hadar beih,
because since now we're talking about theoretically, right, we're talking about theoretically
had you known better would you have done it or not. So
as long as we're talking about theoretically, let's theorize some more. Theoretically,
had בית דין Beis Din become aware that they made a mistake
and you would have known et cetera et cetera, then you wouldn't
have done it, right? Meaning, yes, had you been aware partially that
this was חלב, chelev, you might have done it because given בית
דין's Beis Din ruling, but ultimately you're somebody who wishes you wouldn't
have done this because had בית דין Beis Din found out they
made a mistake and retracted their ruling, then you wouldn't have wanted
to do it. So כיון דכי מישתודע ליה לבי דינא keivan de-ki
mishtoda lei le-vei dina הדרי
בהו hadari behu והוא נמי הדר ביה ve-hu nami hadar beih שב
מידיעתו קרינן ביה וחייב. shav midiato karinan beih ve-chayav. He is somebody
that ideally would not have wanted to do it. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan says when are you חייב chayav a קרבן? korban? That you
made a mistake and you did something that ideally you wouldn't have
wanted to have done. So this is a case as opposed to
the guy who's actively rejects and says I'm ready to eat חמץ.
chametz. Ideally I would have been happy to eat חמץ, chametz, okay,
from the subjective perspective. That's a person who doesn't bring a קרבן.
korban. But you ideally wish you wouldn't have eaten this piece. Why?
Because even though right now בית דין Beis Din has ruled it's
okay, in the end of the day we're going to find out
that they made a mistake and therefore ideally you wish you wouldn't
have eaten it. Okay, so therefore you do bring
a
קרבן. korban. אמר רבא amar Rava מודה רב שאינו משלים לרוב ציבור.
modeh Rav she-eino mashlim le-rov tzibbur.
In this case, if you had let's say exactly fifty percent of
the people followed בית דין Beis Din and ate this חלב chelev
consciously eating this חלב chelev because knowing that בית דין Beis Din
gave the ruling. Now as soon as it's fifty percent plus one
person, בית דין Beis Din is going to bring a קרבן korban
because the majority of the ציבור tzibbur listened to them. You're that
one person, you're that one vote, and you go ahead and you
eat this not because you're consciously following their ruling because you accidentally
ate the wrong piece of meat, okay? So maybe you would have
done it had you known that it was חלב chelev but accidentally
you were really trying to eat something else. Okay, so even if
we say that you personally are פטור patur because you theoretically would
have been prepared to follow their ruling, since it's not—you're not actively
following their ruling, you don't combine with the other fifty percent of
the people to now say that a majority of the people followed
בית דין's Beis Din ruling. Okay, in this case you theoretically would
have listened to them but you didn't listen to them in actuality.
Okay, so מודה רב שאינו משלים לרוב ציבור, modeh Rav she-eino mashlim
le-rov tzibbur, even though you're exempt because you theoretically would have listened
to בית דין Beis Din when you mixed up the pieces of
meat, since you didn't actively listen to them, you don't make it
that the majority of the people listened to them and that they
have to bring a קרבן. korban. מאי טעמא mai taama why? אמר
קרא בשגגה עד שכולם בשגגה אחת. amar kra bishgagah ad she-kulam bishgagah
achas. All of the people have to be following בית דין Beis
Din in the same way. So since they were actively following בית
דין Beis Din and you only theoretically would have followed בית דין,
Beis Din, you don't combine to define the majority of the ציבור.
tzibbur. Okay,
בין שעשו ועשה עמהם, bein she-asu ve-asah imahem, whether he did it
whether they did it and he followed them or whether they didn't
do it at all et cetera. So the גמרא Gemara says למה
לי למיתני כל הני? lama li le-misni kol hanei? Why does it
say all these? בשלמא רישא לא זו אף זו קתני, bishlama reisha
lo zu af zu kasani, not only this even this. Not only
if they actively did it and he did it with them is
he exempt, but even if they didn't do it at all and
he did it, he's exempt. אלא סיפא לחיובא איפכא מיבעי ליה, ela
seifa le-chiuva ipcha mibaei lei, but the end where it's speaking about
the cases where he actually knows
better, it should—if we're talking about לא זו אף זו, lo zu
af zu, it should have said not only if he did it
on his own, even if he did it with them, since he
knows better he's still חייב. chayav. So the גמרא Gemara says זו
ואין צריך לומר זו קתני. zu ve-ein tzarich lomar zu kasani. Fine.
The end of the case is the—it's stylistically the same, the order,
and rather than saying not only this even this case, not only
this even this case, it's saying in this case he's חייב chayav
and obviously in these other cases he's חייב. chayav. Okay, anyway, moving
on. וידע אחת מהן שטעו תלמיד שהורה לעצמו. ve-yada achas me-hen she-tau
talmid she-horah le-atzmo. Now we get to the interesting next case: somebody
knows better, then he's not relying on them, and then he's supposed
to follow his own conscience, not set himself up as a competing
authority but follow his own conscience. תרתי למה לי? Tarti lamah li?
Now why does it say
one
of them or תלמיד וראוי להוראה? talmid ve-ra'uy le-hora'ah? Or no, תרתי
tarti I think, תלמיד וראוי להוראה, talmid ve-ra'uy le-hora'ah, the double language
of תלמיד וראוי להוראה. talmid ve-ra'uy le-hora'ah. Okay, so why is it
sort of saying both? So it says, so the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רבא איצטריך. Amar Rava itztrich. סלקא דעתך אמינא Salka daitach amina
הני מילי גמיר וסביר. hanei milei gamir ve-savir If it just said
תלמיד, talmid, maybe I would have said that somebody has to be
fully fit to be on the court, which means both גמיר, gamir,
they know all of the relevant information, and סביר, savir, they have
good analytical skills, and good judgment, right? Because you need both. You
need to know the substance of the law and you need to
have a good lawyerly mind and whatever, and you know you have
to have good analytical skills. So only that person can I say
is really acting, not really following them. אבל גמיר ולא סביר לא.
Aval gamir velo savir lo. But if somebody just knows the law
but isn't good in terms of like analysis, I might think at
the end of the day he really is following them. Like I
say to myself, look, I'm not as big as sages as they
are, but I know the law and I think that they're making
an obvious mistake here in the law. You could say that if
I decide in the end to follow them, what I'm really doing
is I'm really sort of saying like, at the end of the
day I'm not saying I know they're wrong and I'm following them.
I say like, they probably know better than I do, you know,
they're smarter, they're more analytical even though it looks to me like
they're going against an explicit ruling. So maybe in that case it's
considered to be that I'm not going on my own authority. I
actually genuinely am sort of,
like you know, not just submitting to their authority but trusting in
their judgment over my
judgment. Okay, so therefore the חידוש chiddush is that no, even in
that case, if I think that they're going against the law that
I know is clear, even if I think they're smarter than me
or whatever and I don't have strong analytical skills, at the end
of the day, I'm not following their judgment, you know, I'm not
relying on them. I know better.
Okay, so הני מילי אבל גמיר ולא סביר לא. hanei milei aval
gamir velo savir lo. אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye להוראה le-hora'ah
גמיר וסביר משמע. gamir ve-savir mashma. So what do you mean? How
can you say that? ראוי להוראה Ra'uy le-hora'ah means that he has
all the qualities, both knowledge and analytical skills, and that's the only
case we're talking about. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבא Rava said
back to him, אנא הכי קאמינא, Ana hachi ka-amina, אי מההיא הוה
אמינא ei mehahi hava amina הני מילי hanei milei גמיר וסביר gamir
ve-savir. אבל גמיר ולא סביר לא. aval gamir velo savir lo. If
it had just said תלמיד, talmid, meaning the whole phrase you're right
doesn't suggest what I'm saying. I'm learning what I'm saying
from the duplication of the language. If it had just said תלמיד,
talmid, I would have said it meant you have all the qualities,
you both have the knowledge and the analytical skills.
תנא ראוי להוראה, Tanna ra'uy le-hora'ah, so it has an extra phrase
ראוי להוראה, ra'uy le-hora'ah, משנה יתירה, mishnah yeseirah, אפילו גמיר ולא סביר
סביר ולא גמיר. afilu gamir velo savir savir velo gamir. The extra
stuff one is like אימא רחמנא לריבויא eima rachamana lerevuya type of
thing, you know, because it's more explicit and it says fit to
rule, it really means you have qualities that would make you fit
to rule even if they're not complete. So either you have really
good analytical skills or you have really good knowledge, even though you
only have half of the full package, okay, nevertheless that is sufficient
to say that when you go ahead and they give a ruling
and you say, you know what, I'm just going to listen to
them, that really you do deep down know better. Okay, and you
can't say that because they both have knowledge and analytical skills and
I only have one, I'm really trusting them. No, you're not really
trusting them. You really do know better and you're just listening to
them even though you know you shouldn't be, okay, which is interesting
'cause actually if you ask me, I totally get that idea. Like,
you know, to me it looks obvious that something is one way,
but if I know somebody is much more knowledgeable than I am
or much more has much more better analytical skills, they probably understand
something about this that I don't and I'm genuinely going to trust
them. But the גמרא Gemara is going to say if it looks
to you, you have at least one of those qualities, and to
you it looks like they're making a mistake, then you should not
have done that. You should have followed your own conscience. Okay, so
ראוי להוראה. ra'uy le-hora'ah. כגון מאן? Kigon man? Now who falls in
this category of somebody fit to give פסק? psak? אמר רבא כגון
שמעון בן עזאי ושמעון בן זומא. Amar Rava kigon Shimon ben Azzai
ve-Shimon ben Zoma. So those were two people that were like big
clerks of the court, תלמידים talmidim sitting in front of the main
court of the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, and they could have been on the
court, but you know, there just wasn't a vacancy, but they were
fit to be on the court. אמר ליה אביי כי האי גוונא
מזיד הוא. Amar lei Abaye ki hai gavna mezid hu. I don't
get it. If they're fit to be on the court, and now
you could have asked that from the משנה mishnah itself, the משנה
mishnah says one of them knows they're wrong, one of the court
itself knows they're wrong. So אביי Abaye says, why is it if
you yourself are on the court or fit to be on the
court and know that they're making a mistake and you listen to
them, why do you bring a קרבן? korban? You should be considered
a willful violator of the law. You know they're in error. Okay,
where's your mistake? So I get why you're not exempt, but why
you know, you're מזיד, mezid, you're more liable. You don't get to
bring a קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says לטעמיך הא דתניא.
le-ta'amich ha detanya. One minute we have a ברייתא *baraita* that says
explicitly this: ועשותה *v'asotah* הא יחיד העושה מפי עצמו חייב *ha yachid
ha'oseh mipi atzmo chayav* ומפי בית דין baisdin פטור *u'mipi Beis Din
patur*. If you make your own mistake you bring a קרבן korban,
*korban*, if you're following בית דין baisdin *Beis Din* you're exempt. כיצד
*Keitzad*? What's the כיצד *keitzad*? הורו בית דין baisdin, שחלב מותר *horu
Beis Din she'cheilev muttar* ונודע לאחד מהם שטעה *ve'nodah l'echad mehem she'ta'ah*,
one of them knows they're making a mistake, או תלמיד ויושב לפניהם
וראוי להוראה *o talmid v'yosheiv lifneihem v'raui l'hora'ah*, somebody who's sitting in
front of them and is fit to be on the court, כגון
שמעון בן עזאי *k'gon Shimon Ben Azzai*, יכול יהא פטור *yachol yehei
patur*, maybe even in that case you're exempt for listening to them?
תלמוד לומר בעשותה *Talmud lomar ba'asotah* אחת יחיד העושה על פי עצמו
חייב *achat yachid ha'oseh al pi atzmo chayav*. If at the end
of the day you're following, you know better and you're doing it,
you're חייב *chayav* a קרבן korban. *korban*. ומבית דין *u'mibeis din* if
you don't know better and you're following them, פטור *patur*, you're exempt.
אלא היכי משכחת לה *ela heichi mashkachat lah*? So what's the example?
כגון דידע דאסור *k'gon d'yada d'assur*. If they're so, if they know
בית דין baisdin *Beis Din* is making a mistake, what makes them
a שוגג *shogeg*? כגון דידע דאסור *k'gon d'yada d'assur*. Yes, you know
that it's forbidden, so why are you a שוגג *shogeg*? דקא טעי
במצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים chachamim *de'ka ta'ei be'mitzvah lishmoa divrei chachamim*. And
the error that they're making is that they think that you have
to listen to the sages even if they're wrong. ודידי נמי דטעה
במצוה לשמוע דברי חכמים *v'didi nami d'ta'ah be'mitzvah lishmoa divrei chachamim*. So
me too. So here's the case. This is so relevant for how
we think what makes הלכה *halacha* because everybody knows the famous רש"י
*Rashi* that says, right, when it says לא תסור ימין ושמאל *lo
sasur yamin u'smol*, don't sway to the right or the left, רש"י
*Rashi* says אפילו אומרים לך על ימין שהוא שמאל ועל שמאל שהוא
ימין *afilu omrim lacha al yamin she'hu smol v'al smol she'hu yamin*.
Even if it looks like they're telling you that your right hand
is your left hand and your left hand is your right hand.
Right, so that makes it sound like even when you know they're
making a mistake, you listen to them. And here the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is saying explicitly that's not true. Now maybe that's true for
a layperson because a layperson could think they're making a mistake and
a layperson doesn't know better. But if you're fit to be on
the court and in your mind they're making a mistake, it is
wrong to think that you're supposed to, that they're supposed to follow
them even when they make an error. That's what you think, you
think you're supposed to do that, okay? And therefore when you ate
this חלב *cheilev*, you were not a willful violator of the חלב
*cheilev*, you actually thought that you had permission to eat it. You
thought that the court's ruling is always authoritative even in the face
of error. Now the funny thing is like that gets to this
question: One minute, isn't that true? Meaning if the, if it's an
over, if like isn't their interpretation always binding? And that again gets
to the case that no, that there are some cases where we
can say their interpretation is objectively wrong. What are those cases is
not clear, but if there are cases where we can say it's
objectively wrong and you know that to be the case, then you
do not listen to them. Even though it says don't sway to
the right or the left, it does not apply to a case
when they're objectively wrong, which then again just begs the question: then
what's so bad about the זקן ממרא *Zaken Mamre*? And the answer
is what's bad about him is that he positioned himself as a
competing authority. Okay, but exactly, but to actually just follow your own
conscience when you know they're wrong, that's what you're required to do.
So there's a whole range of cases, right? There's a case where
it's like I think they're wrong, as far as I understand this
הלכה *halacha* they're making a mistake, but they're smarter than me, I'm
just going to rely on them. And the גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* says
like actually if you really are knowledgeable enough to know that they're
wrong, even if a little bit you're sort of like saying, ach,
they're smarter than me, that itself is considered to be relying on
yourself and not relying on them. And in that case you actually
bring a קרבן korban *korban* as well. And then there's a case
where like I say I absolutely know they're wrong, but I think
I'm supposed to listen to them anyway. That also is a case
where you're at the end of the day not just following them,
not just relying on them, okay, and you also bring a קרבן
korban *korban*, okay, because you yourself know better and the fact that
you think you're supposed to listen to them is just really a
mistake. Okay, so those are cases where you are a שוגג *shogeg*
but not a שוגג על פיהם *shogeg al pihem*. You're making a
mistake but at the end of the day you should have known
better and you're seen as acting on your own authority. Okay, so
now it says like this. זה הכלל התולה בעצמו חייב *zeh hakeilal
hatoleh be'atzmo chayav*. This is the principle: if you rely on yourself
you're חייב *chayav*. לאתויי מאי *le'asuyei mai*? לאתויי מבעט בהוראה *le'asuyei meva'et
b'hora'ah*. Let's say somebody says I don't trust, I don't accept the
authority of the court, okay, I think they're always making mistakes, I
regularly reject their rulings. So if they go ahead and they say,
I don't know, they, you know, they say לא תבשל גדי בחלב
אמו *lo svashel gdi b'chalev imo* means all meat and milk, and
I say, yes, they don't know what they're talking about, as long
as it's not a kid goat in its mother's milk and I
go ahead and I eat general בשר בחלב *basar b'chalav* and I
do all these things. Then they come along and they say oh
actually it's מותר *muttar* in this type of a case to eat
this fat and I say oh great, I like that פסק psak
*psak*, I'm going to follow it. So in that case since you
are deciding now to listen to them and in general we see
an attitude that you're making decisions for yourself, you don't submit to
their authority, so even now you're doing this is not in submission
to their authority. You have positioned yourself as somebody who generally just
makes your own decisions and doesn't listen to their rulings. So now
that you're listening to their ruling, we don't say that that's because
of a stance of following them, in the end it's because you've
decided on your own you wanted to do it, okay, and therefore
you would be חייב *chayav*. תולה בבית דין לאתויי *toleh be'veis din
le'asuyei*? Now what's the, what do we include when we say anybody
who relies on בית דין baisdin. *Beis Din* is exempt? הורו בית
דין baisdin וידעו שטעו וחזרו בהן *horu Beis Din v'yadu she'ta'u v'chazru
bahen*. So a case where you followed בית דין *Beis Din* but
you... You were following בית דין after בית דין had retracted. Just
the word didn't get to you that they retracted. You got it?
בית דין said it was okay to eat this thing, you heard
that initial ruling, you went home, two days later and you ate
it. By the time you got home they had retracted, but you
hadn't heard of the retraction. In that case, since in your mind
you were following them, even though in practice the פסק was no
longer binding, okay, you're still exempt. So the גמרא says הא בהדיא
קתני לה, ha b'hedya katani lah, we're going to teach that in
a minute in the following משנה. Mishnah. תני והדר מפרש. tani v'hadar
mefareish. Okay, we're going to teach it and and yes, fine, it's
implicit in this משנה, Mishnah, it's going to be explicit in the
next. Let's just read a tiny bit more. אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל: amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel: זו דברי רב יהודה. zu divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. This idea that everybody could be exempt. An individual follows
בית דין, בית דין is exempt, it's not the majority of the
ציבור, tzibur, the individual is exempt, he's following בית דין. That's the
position of רב יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. וחכמים אומרים, vachachamim omrim, but the
Sages say: יחיד שעשה בהוראת בית דין חייב. yachid she'asah b'horat baisdin
chayav. That anytime בית דין doesn't bring a קרבן, korban. you would
bring a קרבן. korban So even though you are a total innocent
person who has total אמונת חכמים emunas chachamim and you listen to
them and you trusted them and you followed it and you're blameless,
since they're not bringing a קרבן korban because it's only the minority
of the community, not the majority of כל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, since
they're not bringing a קרבן korban and an עבירה aveirah was done,
you're going to bring the קרבן. korban Now this is important because
it gets to the question Devorah was asking before. There's a general
assumption that the reason you bring a קרבן korban is that you
had some guilt, some fault. The sin was, you know, to some
degree blameworthy. We focus very much on this personal sense of guilt
and I'm coming to atone for my personal guilt, okay? And actually
in the תורה, Torah, it's much less about your personal guilt. It's
much less about the fact that when a sin is done, it
creates some like metaphysical rupture in the world or it brings some
טומאה tumah to the world, right? And therefore that bad stuff out
there has to be fixed, right? So it's not so much, I
don't care whether you're to blame, like I care that you're the
cause of it. You walk into a store and you accidentally knock
something over and you break it. It's like, I don't care if
that was an accident. I don't care if you're blameless. You break
it, you clean it up, you know, you know? So therefore, so
that's the idea here is I totally am innocently followed the court,
but since it's not a circumstance that the court brings a קרבן
korban, because it's only an individual, not the majority, so at the
end of the day it was my act, I have to I
made a mess, I clean it up, even if I have no
fault for it and no blame. It's like the גמרא's idea that
if somebody is a תינוק שנשבה, tinok shenishba, an infant who's taken
captive, grows up thinking they're not Jewish, they finally at the end
of 40 years realize that they're Jewish, they have to bring a
קרבן korban. for all of their חילול שבת. chilul Shabbos. Now not
one קרבן for every שבת, Shabbos, maybe one קרבן for all the
שבתות, Shabbos's, but why are they bringing anything? They're totally blameless! Their
whole life they thought that they were, you know, Christian or whatever.
So the answer is it's not about blame, it's about you did
it, somebody's got to bring a קרבן, somebody's got to sweep up
all the broken glass. So what, should somebody else sweep up the
glass? You sweep up the glass, okay? So that is a very
important idea about קרבנות korbanos and this is what we actually say,
that the position of the חכמים is not that is not that
everybody gets off. Even though you were blameless, you still have to
bring a קרבן. Okay and let's just read one more sentence and
we'll end here, I know we're a little bit over, but מאי
רב יהודה mai Rabbi Yehuda and you know what, let's end here,
okay? So because then it's going to get into, we'll have to
figure out how to catch up, but okay, we're already behind, great
start, okay. But we got a lot of very important ideas down,
so we will continue with this tomorrow. What?